Finding Aid for the Dorothy Arzner Papers PASC.0175
UCLA Library Special Collections
Dorothy Arzner papers
circa 1920-1979
UCLA Library Special Collections
Arzner, Dorothy, 1900-1979
PASC.0175
3.5 Linear Feet (7 boxes)
Collection consists of clippings, sketches, photographs and motion picture stills, correspondence, scrapbooks, audio recordings, and ephemera related to Dorothy Arzner's personal life and career as filmmaker. Includes stills the films Anybody's Woman, The Bride Wore Red, The Covered Wagon, Craig's Wife, Dance Girl Dance, Fashion for Women, First Comes Courage, Get Your Man, Manhattan Cocktail, Merrily We Go To Hell, Nana, Old Ironsides, Ten Modern Commandments, and Working Girls.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: This collection contains processed audiovisual materials. All requests to access audiovisual materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mildred Sumner, 1985.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 994622503606533
Biography
Arzner was born Jan. 3, 1900; studied medicine at Univ. of So. CA; ambulance driver in WWI (1917-18); in 1919, she was hired by William C. De Mille as a stenographer in the script dept. at Famous Players-Lasky (Paramount), and was later promoted to script clerk, film cutter, and film editor; editor for Realart, a subsidiary of Paramount, 1922; wrote and edited "Old Ironsides," 1925; met Marion Morgan, choreographer and dancer, in the early 1930s and the two remained companions until Morgan's death in 1971; retired from directing in 1943; produced WAC training films during WWII; taught at UCLA and made commercials for Pepsi-Cola; her credits include, "Christopher Strong" (1933), "Nana" (1934), and "Craig's Wife" (1936); honored at the 1st International Festival of Women's Films, NY, 1972, and by Director's Guild of America, 1975; died Oct. 1, 1979 in La Quinta, CA.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of clippings, sketches, photographs and motion picture stills, correspondence, scrapbooks, audio recordings, and ephemera related to Arzner's personal life and career as filmmaker. Includes stills the films Anybody's Woman, The Bride Wore Red, The Covered Wagon, Craig's Wife, Dance Girl Dance, Fashion for Women, First Comes Courage, Get Your Man, Manhattan Cocktail, Merrily We Go To Hell, Nana, Old Ironsides, Ten Modern Commandments, and Working Girls.
Organization
Arranged in the following series:
Audio recordings (box 2)
Clippings (box 5)
Negatives (box 6)
Personal sketches (box 5)
Personal photographs (boxes 5-6)
Personal correspondence (box 7)
Scrapbooks (boxes 1,3,4)
Stills (box 6)
Tributes (boxes 6-7)
Writings by and about Arzner (box 7)
Women motion picture producers and directors -- Archives.; Arzner, Dorothy, 1900-1979 -- Archives
- Audio recordings
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: This collection contains processed audiovisual materials. All requests to access audiovisual materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
  - DGA Tribute to Dorothy Arzner Reel 1 of 5, 1975 January 25; pasc_0175_002_001; Ida Lupino, 1918-1995; Directors Guild of America; 1 Sound Recordings (1 1/4 inch audiotape; Duration: 0:14:14) 7 inch (Box 2, Case 1)
    Conditions Governing Access
    CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Audiovisual materials are available for access. All requests to access digital materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
    Scope and Contents
    Transcribed from container: Original; Voices of- Doug Morrison, Joelle Debrew, Ida Lupino
    Arzner, Dorothy, 1900-1979
  - DGA Tribute to Dorothy Arzner Reel 2 of 5, 1975 January 25; pasc_0175_002_002; McCall, Mary C., Jr., 1904-1986; Directors Guild of America; 1 Sound Recordings (1 1/4 inch audiotape; Duration: 0:16:17) 7 inch (Box 2, Case 2)
    Transcribed from container: Original
  - DGA Tribute to Dorothy Arzner Reel 3 of 5, 1975 January 25; pasc_0175_002_003; Folsey, George J., 1898-1988; Wellman, William A., 1896-1975; Directors Guild of America; 1 Sound Recordings (1 1/4 inch audiotape; Duration: 0:14:15) 7 inch (Box 2, Case 3)
    Content note: Features the reading of telegrams from Mayor Tom Bradley, Joe Mankiewicz, Lucille Ball, and Katherine Hepburn, and Frank Capra.
  - DGA Tribute to Dorothy Arzner Reel 4 of 5, 1975 January 25; pasc_0175_002_004; O'Hara, Shirley; Coppola, Francis Ford, 1939-; Directors Guild of America; 1 Sound Recordings (1 1/4 inch audiotape; Duration: 0:16:19) 7 inch (Box 2, Case 4)
    Content note: Features the reading of a telegrams from CA Secretary of State March Fong Eu, Fay Wray, Louie Hayward, Fredrick March, Rosalind Russel, Joan Crawford,
  - DGA Tribute to Dorothy Arzner Reel 5 of 5, 1975 January 25; pasc_0175_002_005; Ballard, Lucien, 1908-1988; Directors Guild of America; 1 Sound Recordings (1 1/4 inch audiotape; Duration: 0:11:04) 7 inch (Box 2, Case 5)
  - DGA Tribute to Dorothy Arzner Part 1 of 2, undated; pasc_0175_002_006a; Ida Lupino, 1918-1995; Directors Guild of America; 1 Sound Recordings (1 audiocassette; Duration: 0:44:49) (Box 2, Case 6)
  - DGA Tribute to Dorothy Arzner Part 2 of 2 / Fragment of King Vidor Talk, undated; pasc_0175_002_006b; Vidor, King, 1894-1982; Directors Guild of America; 1 Sound Recordings (1 audiocassette; Duration: 0:46:47) (Box 2, Case 6)
    Content note: Recording transitions to "K. Vidor Talk" at 0:28:00
  - DGA Arzner Tribute, Reel 1 and Reel 2, undated; pasc_0175_002_007a; Ida Lupino, 1918-1995; Directors Guild of America; 1 Sound Recordings (1 audiocassette; Duration: 0:30:33) (Box 2, Case 7)
  - DGA Arzner Tribute, Reel 3, undated; pasc_0175_002_007b; Ida Lupino, 1918-1995; Directors Guild of America; 1 Sound Recordings (1 audiocassette; Duration: 0:14:40) (Box 2, Case 7)
  - Dorothy Arzner At Diablo Valley College, 1976 October 13; pasc_0175_002_008a; Arzner, Dorothy, 1900-1979; Diablo Valley College; 1 Sound Recordings (1 audiocassette; Duration: 0:46:51) (Box 2, Case 8)
  - Dorothy Arzner At Diablo Valley College, 1976 October 13; pasc_0175_002_008b; Arzner, Dorothy, 1900-1979; Diablo Valley College; 1 Sound Recordings (1 audiocassette; Duration: 0:02:55) (Box 2, Case 8)
- Clippings
  - Includes tributes to Dorothy Arzner, and commentary and announcements related to festivals featuring her films, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Includes articles pertaining to women filmmakers in general with mention of Dorothy Arzner, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Five (5) issues of "Camera: the Digest of the Motion Picture Industry" (fragile). Includes 1922, Vol. 5 no.'s 16, 24, 26, 28, 29, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Negatives
  - Sixty-nine (69) negatives of clippings in scrapbooks and photographs in this collection. Negs are numbered DA1-DA69. Availablity is marked on verso of photographs or on the page of scrapbooks. STORED IN Performing Arts Special Collections - NEGATIVE FILES, undated
  - One (1) 8x10 negative of Dorothy Arzner with film strip, two (2) strips of La Quinta home, four (4) strips Morgan Dancers, one (1) strip of young Dorothy Arzner. six(6) contact strips of outings with friends, undated (Box 6, Folder 26)
- Personal sketches
  - Nine (9) pencil sketches, one (1) ink sketch (all unsigned). Orignal envelope labeled "Sketches by Dorothy Arzner and Marion Morgan", undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Eight (8) items including seven (7) pencil sketches and one (1) pastel. Four (4) items signed D. Arzner, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Personal photographs
  - Oversized portraits of Dorothy Arzner. Seven (7) items, (2) inscribed by Dorothy Arzner, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - One (1) oversize photograph labeled "Entrance Atrium 2249 Mountain Oak Dr. Home of Marion Morgan and Dorothy Arzner 1930 - 1951", undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Forty (40) items including small snap shots of Dorothy Arzner and friends. Includes snap shot of Marlene Dietrich holding Dorothy Arzner's Siamese cat, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Fifty-seven (57) items. Includes small photos of young Dorothy Arzner, family, and friends, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Twenty (20) items. Includes photographs of Dorothy Arzner and family from childhood to adolesence, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Twenty-one (21) items. Includes (1) portrait of a young Dorothy Arzner and Marion Morgan, two (2) snap shots of Dorothy Arzner bust by Alice Bush Lewis, and photos of older Dorothy Arzner at Diablo College, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Fifteen (15) items including portraits of Dorothy Arzner early in her career, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Twenty (20) items including photographs of Dorothy Arzner at work on various projects, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Fifty-six (56) items. Includes several photographs sent to Dorothy Arzner by Marion Morgan from [Europe]. [Items are undated, possible date 1920's or 1930's]. (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - (Dates unknown) Seventeen items including cards, letters and postcards. Includes (8) postcards from Aunt Emma addressed to Emma [Dorothy's middle name] and Dave, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - (1930'S - 1940's) Twenty-three items including postcards and letters to Dorothy Arzner, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - (1970'S) Forty-three letters, cards, and post cards to Dorothy Arzner, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
    Includes personal and professional work related correspondence. One Christmas card from Marion Morgan dated Christmas 1969.
  - Forty-four postcards from Marion Morgan to Dorothy Arzner dates spanning, circa 1920s - 1940s (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Forty-three postcards from Marion Morgan to Dorothy Arzner, circa 1930s (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Ten (10) assorted letters, cards, and postcards to Marion Morgan, mostly from 1971 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Fifty-three (53) postcards, letters, cards, and telegrams. Condolences to Dorothy Arzner concerning the death of Marion Morgan, undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Seven (7) items including (2) coat of arms for Arzner, (1) Westlake School for Girls Record, death certificates for Dorothy Arzner, David Arzner, Mabel Arzner, and Lois Arzner, undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Scrapbooks
  - One (1) red scrapbook (fragile). Includes photos of young Dorothy Arzner, family, and friends, undated (Box 1)
  - Three (3) items (fragile). One "Presented to Dorothy Arner from Joe Dill" includes small snap shots from "Old Ironsides". Two remaining include photos of Dorothy Arzner, family, and friends, undated (Box 3)
  - "Dorothy Arzner Press Book", hand made (fragile), clippings, 1926 - 1980 (Box 4)
- Stills
  - "ANYBODY'S WOMAN (1930, Paramount). Six (6) items including photographs of Dorothy Arzner at work, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - "BEHIND THE MAKE UP" (1930, Paramount). One (1) photograph of Fay Wray and William Powell, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - "THE BRIDE WORE RED" (1937, MGM). Twelve (12) photographs including Dorothy Arzner at work, Joan Crawford, and Franchot Tone, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - "THE COVERED WAGON" (1923, Paramount). Three (3) photographs, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - "CRAIG'S WIFE" (1936, Columbia). Nine (9) photographs including Dorothy Arzner at work, John Boles, Rosalind Russell, Billie Burke, and Mary McCall, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - "DANCE GIRL DANCE" (1940, RKO). Eleven (11) photographs including Dorothy Arzner at work and home, Lucille Ball, and one inscribed photograph from James Anderson, undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - "FASHION FOR WOMEN" (1927, Famous Players Lasky/Paramount). Three (3) photographs including Dorothy Arzner at work, undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - "FIRST COMES COURAGE" (1943, Columbia). One (1) photograph of Carl Esmond, Merle Oberon, and Brian Aherne, undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - "GET YOUR MAN" (1934, Paramount). Eleven (11) photographs including shots of various scenes, undated (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - "MANHATTAN COCKTAIL" (1928, Famous Players Lasky/Paramount). Six (6) photographs including Dorothy Arzner at work, undated (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - "MERRILY WE GO TO HELL" (1932, Paramount). Four (4) photographs including Dorothy Arzner at work, undated (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - "NANA" (1934, United Artists). One (1) photograph labeled "Anna Sten in the Samuel Goldwyn Production of NANA". Shows Dorothy Arzner at work, undated (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - "OLD IRONSIDES" (1926, Paramount). Fifty-six (56) photographs including Dorothy Arzner working, Esther Ralston, Wallace Berry, George Bancroft, George Godfrey, and Charles Farrell, undated (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - "TEN MODERN COMMANDMENTS" (1927, Paramount). Four (4) photographs including Dorothy Arzner at work, undated (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - WAC'S TRAINING FILM (1944). Two (2) publicity stills of Dorothy Arzner with WACS World War II, undated (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - WORKING GIRLS (1931, Paramount). Two (2) photographs including Dorothy Arzner with telephone operators, and Dorothy Hall and Judith Wood, undated (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Five (5) miscellaneous photographs. Includes (2) photographs of Billie Burke, (1) photograph of drapes in a hotel suite, (1) photograph of Charles the Second, and (1) unidentified group of actors, undated (Box 6, Folder 25)
- Tributes
  - Five (5) photographs from the Director's Guild Tribute to Dorothy Arzner. Includes Dorothy Arnzer, William Wellman, Fay Wray, Robert Wise, Daisy Gerber, Francis Ford Coppola, Lucien Ballard, Mary McCall, Jr., Margaret Lindsay, and Francine Parker, undated (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Two (2) programs: "Director's Guild of America A Tribute to Dorothy Arzner Pioneer Director". One with picture of Dorothy Arzner, undated (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Twenty-six (26) items. Correspondence to Dorothy Arzner about the Director's Guild Tribute. Includes telegrams and letters from Katherine Hepburn, Joan Crawford, Robert Young, Rosalind Russell, Fredric March, Lucille Ball, Frank Capra, and others, undated (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Fourteen programs for film festivals. (4) programs featuring Dorothy Arzner's work specifically. (10) programs featuring women film makers in general including Dorothy Arzner, undated (Box 7, Folder 16)
- Writings by Dorothy Arzner
  - "Starlight", [n.d.], 3 page writing philosophy on the influence of movies on people's lives, undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Four (4) studio biographies. (1) untitled, (1) Director's file Publicity, (1) M.G.M. Director's file, (3) M.G.M. Publicity Director's file - (1) annotated, undated (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Senior thesis, 91 pages. "What Is This We Hear - A Broad Is Gonna Direct?" by Deborah Derow, May, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - "The Work of Dorothy Arzner: Towards a Feminist Cinema" edited by Claire Johnston. Published by the British Film Institute, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - "Approaching the Art of Arzner" by Francine Parker, [n.d.], 14 pages, undated (Box 7, Folder 13)